I want you to imagine that somebody sent
you these six slides. How would they
make you feel? I know the first time
that I scanned them, I felt both
overwhelmed and confused at the exact
same time. Now, the most common reason
that presentations don't work out, is
because folks don't spend enough time
planning, thinking critically about the
people on the receiving end, what they
care about, exploring different
narrative flows, and truly defining what
success will look like. This is the
exact topic that I dive deep into in
chapter nine of our brand new book,
Storytelling with Data before and after.
I share all of the strategy and
thoughtful planning that I have to do to
turn these six slides into something
that is truly actionoriented. Now, in
this video, I'm going to share the
results of that thoughtful planning and
what that presentation could have looked
and sounded like. Let's jump in.
We are quickly approaching the launch of
our brand new customer service model. In
fact, we are just one month away from
that go live date. So, I'd like to have
an open and honest discussion today
about where we stand. Now, we'll start
specifically by reviewing why we need a
new approach to customer service in the
first place. And then we'll take a look
at the project timeline and discuss
where we are today with regards to go
live and answer the very important
question, are we ready? So, let's start
with the first item on the agenda.
Now, it's easy to forget what our goals
were with this project, but to put it
simply, our current approach to customer
service doesn't work. It doesn't work
for our employees, and most importantly,
it doesn't work for our customers. Now,
in a recent employee survey, one
customer service representative shared,
"Things are frustrating right now. I
don't feel like I'm helping customers as
effectively as I should be." This
sentiment was further supported when we
started to look at our customer
satisfaction scores. So to break this
down for you, we'll look at satisfaction
scores across a couple of different
dimensions. Along the vertical axis, we
have satisfaction scores from our
customers that recently interacted with
the team. And this is the proportion of
folks that feel positively after
interacting with us. And you can see
that overall our satisfaction score is
right around 84%.
We have incredibly high standards on
this team and our goal is always to be
at or above 95%.
Now, we can break down these
satisfaction scores by the time that it
takes to resolve a given ticket. And
when we do this, I'd like you to notice
two things. First, the longer it takes
to resolve a given ticket, the lower the
satisfaction scores tend to be. This is
evident by the decreasing bars as you
scan from left to right. I'd also like
to call out that even when we resolve a
ticket quickly within 24 hours or 48
hours,
the scores are still below that minimum
threshold of 95%. So, what this tells me
is that our approach isn't working. But
our new plan will. Our new plan is a
massive departure from what we know
today. We'll take the entire customer
service department and divide it into
two highly specialized teams. It will
have better staffing which will enable
us to provide faster and more effective
responses to our customers. But doing
this takes time. So I want to shift next
to the project timeline. And I'll admit
when I look at this, we were a bit
ambitious when we first embarked on this
project. We actually estimated it would
take approximately 9 months if we
started in February. Now we divided all
of the tasks necessary to complete this
overhaul into four main phases. We've
got our planning phase, communication
related tasks, reporting updates, and
most importantly, all of the training
that would be necessary. Now, we are
well into this effort, which means we
have already completed the first three
phases of this project. And I am happy
to report that we were able to adhere
strictly to this project timeline for
phases 1 through three. But that means
we are currently in phase four, all
about training. And our training phase
is divided into three highle modules. We
have on the job training, product
knowledge as well as skills training.
And according to this timeline, we
should be within that third module.
Unfortunately, that isn't the case. We
severely underestimated how long it
would take us to complete that first
module. This is largely in part to the
increased call volume that the
representatives are facing on the floor,
impeding them from actually completing
their training. A more realistic
timeline means it would take us
approximately five months to complete
that first on the job module as well as
an additional two months needed to
complete the second modules product
knowledge and skills training. So just
to quickly summarize where we stand
within this fourth module, we are
currently about 60% of the way through
the first module and most of the team
still needs to complete their second and
their third training modules. Good news
is is that these final modules are much
shorter to complete in duration. So
coming back to where we started, I know
folks are concerned and as the project
manager, I am also too concerned, which
is why I'm recommending that we need to
strongly consider delaying go live, take
the rest of the year to fully train our
staff. That way we can start the next
year with our brand new model and ensure
that our employees and our customers are
both happy.
Now, if you enjoyed that transformation
and you like learning via examples, then
you are going to love our brand new
book, Storytelling with Data Before and
After. It's co-authored by myself and
colleagues Cole Naspck and Mike
Cisneros. And together, we share 20
examples of how we helped our clients
transform their business communications.
I'll leave links in the description
below if you want to grab yourself a
copy. And if you have any questions
about the book, be sure to let us know
in the comments.